	
<section>
	<title>Modelling Graphs</title>
	<label>graphs</label>
	<para> 
      In this section we discuss various ways of representing directed graphs, the different 
      shapes that their entity models can take and the different organisations of information implied by the different shapes.
	</para>

	<subsection>
		<title>Directed Graphs</title>
		<para> There is a reliance here, in this presentation, on the use of the work <q>abstract</q> and 
        on an understanding of what the mathematician means by this. 
        The best that I can offer as explanation is that the mathematical idea of an abstract structure 
        is that of a set of individuals and relations independent of any particular 
        representation of the individuals and the mathematical concepts of <emph>graph</emph> and <emph>directed graph</emph> are cases in point.
        In the case of a graph the individuals are notionally
        vertices and edges and the relations are the
        incidence relations between them. Paradoxically, with regard to any particular 
        abstract structure, to describe it we need <emph>some</emph> kind 
        of representation even though what we seek to describe is something <emph>without any</emph> particular representation.  Mathematican Robin Gandy describes this to a non-mathematical audience in 
        a lecture <q>Structure in Mathematics</q>
			<footnote>In <emph>Structuralism, edited by D. Robey, 
            Wolfson College Lectures, 1972</emph>.</footnote>; he draws the love 
        relationships to be found in Iris Murdoch's novel Severed Head as a 
        directed graph and in a later section later I draw an equivalent graph (figure <figref>lovegraph</figref>).
        If we abstract a directed graph from this then there are no labels, no lines, 
        no points on paper just the facts of a set of notional individual entities and the
        relationships between them<footnote>According to Gandy: This indifference to form of <emph>representation</emph>
          is what Bertrand Russell referred to when he said that in mathematics we are not interested in 
          what we are talking about. We return to the subject abstraction versus representation in a later section.</footnote>. 
		</para>

		<para> We gave one model of a directed graph earlier as an example of a conjunctive dependency it is reproduced below in figure <figref>directedGraph4</figref>.
		</para>
		<figureOfPicture>
			<pictureName>directedGraph4</pictureName>
			<width>35%</width>
			<caption>The model of a directed graph.</caption>
		</figureOfPicture>


</subsection>
	
	<subsection>
		<title>ER Models of Directed Graph</title>

		<para> Viewing figures <figref>loveRelationship2</figref> and following on from figure <figref>loveRelationship2</figref> we see that there are two 
        further ways of modelling directed graphs. These are shown in figure <figref>directedGraph1</figref> and <figref>directedGraph2</figref>.
		</para>

		<figuregroup>
			<figureOfPicture>
				<width>4cm</width>
				<pictureName>directedGraph1</pictureName>
				<caption>
            Directed Graph ER Model (ii)
				</caption>
			</figureOfPicture>

			<figureOfPicture>
				<width>4cm</width>
				<pictureName>directedGraph2</pictureName>
				<caption>
            Directed Graph ER Model (iii)
				</caption>
			</figureOfPicture>
		</figuregroup>
		<newline/>

		<para> Though we have given three ways of modelling directed graphs note that mathematically there is only a single concept. 
        The different models represent different ways of localising and communicating the information content of a graph. 
        The models in figures <figref>directedGraph1</figref> and <figref>directedGraph2</figref> vary the incidence relationships between edges and vertices between 
        categories <emph>reference</emph> and <emph>composition</emph>. If both are made composition then we get a further variation which is shown in 
        figure <figref>directedGraph4</figref>.
		</para>
<!--
		<figureOfPicture>
			<width>4cm</width>
			<pictureName>directedGraph4</pictureName>
			<caption>
          Directed Graph ER Model (iv)
			</caption>
		</figureOfPicture>
-->
	
		<para> We mentioned in chapter one that information is usually hierarchically communicated whereas with double composition relationships there is not one hierarchy but two hierarchies. Information must 
        be double communicated once in each hierarchical form. 
        For linear, hierarchical communication the above model is 
        therefore replaced by one in which both hierarchies are represented as shown in figure <figref>directedGraph3</figref>.
			<figureOfPicture>
				<pictureName>directedGraph3</pictureName>
				<width>5cm</width>
				<caption>
            Directed Graph ER Model (v)
				</caption>
			</figureOfPicture>
		</para>
	</subsection>
	<subsection>
		<title>Modelling Graphs and Symmetric Relationships</title>
		<para>
        We use the unqualified term graph to mean a set of vertices and a set of undirected connections 
        or <entity>edges</entity>s between them. To the mathematician the definition is straightforward but to the entity
        modeller it is less so and is somewhat unsatisfying. 
        There is a difficulty and this difficulty lies at the heart of entity modelling. 
        An understanding of the difficulty reveals simultaneously a gap in the entity relational 
        approach by comparison with the mathematical approach but also an affinity between it and the means of language and communication.
		</para>

		<para> To model a bidirectional graph is to add a reverse relationship to any of the models of a directed graph. 
        If we start from figure <figref>directedGraph1</figref> then we get this model:
			<er_center>
				<filename>graphUnnormalised</filename>
			</er_center>
		</para>

		<para> In this model we have greyed out the <entity>to</entity> relationship to show that it has become redundant. 
        This is because the vertex that an exit leads to is always the same vertex that its reverse leads from. 
		</para>
	</subsection>
</section>
