
<chapter>
  <title>The Author</title>
  <subtitle>About the Author</subtitle>
  <label>finalthoughts</label>
 
  <preface>
    <para>
      The author of this book/website is John Cartmell;  you can find me 
      on  <a href="https://uk.linkedin.com/pub/john-cartmell/43/a08/b1a">LinkedIn</a> or you could email 
      me as john.w.cartmell on gmail.  I was taught mathematics at the University of Bristol where H. Rose, B. Rotman and others taught me both Abstract Algebra and Mathematical Logic
      and  where F. Rowbotham went on to teach me Category Theory and also to supervise my M.Sc. dissertation after A. Champenowne had introduced 
      me to Lawere Theories.  D. Scott kindly supervised my D.Phil at Oxford where P. Hancock intoduced me to Martin-Lof type theory 
      and thus to types that vary -- the subject of my D.Phil. Early on in my programming career I was fortunate to work in a team led by M. Falla and 
      pioneering object-oriented software. I learnt databases and implemented my first database working to designs of A. Alderson
      who in the process taught me databases and also requirements analysis and software design. Working at the University of Edinburgh 
      with R. Burstall and G. Richie I learnt the utility of attribute grammars and some of the notation in this book I learnt from
      working with and implementing designs of Harry Ellis. 
      The distinction between reference and composition I learnt working on the PCTE+ project, sometime 
      alongside the CAIS project team. 
      New relational design theory has been in the back of my mind since I worked at Ipsys with A. Alderson, A. Elliott, B. Passingham and F. Smit.
      It finally came together while I was working on Laboratory Workflow systems at Cyprotex - an opportunity given to me by D. Leahy and where 
      discussions with B. Appleyard has been particularly supportive. A strikingly successful application of 
      the methods and tools has been at Cyprotex Discovery in a mid-2016 project that produced
      LCMS Chromatography Analysis Software overcoming deficiencies in the Mass Spectrometry supplier's 
      own software so as to improve the productivity of scientists.
      For that project we implemented entity models in XML and generated code in typescript and python.
    </para>

    <para>
      For xslt I am gratefully for and acknowledge and recommend the Saxon xslt implementation which is also used
      to produce the svg images on this website; likewise I have
      benefitted from excellent articles on xslt from Lenz Consulting (for example <a href="http://lenzconsulting.com/how-xslt-works/">How XSLT Works</a>).  
    </para>
    <subsection>
      <title>My Bibliography</title>
      <para>
        Cartmell J. (1978) 
        Generalised Algebraic Theories and Contextual Categories,
        PhD Thesis, Oxford.
      </para>
      <para>
        Cartmell J. (1986) 
        Generalised Algebraic Theories and Contextual Categories,
        in Annals of Pure and Applied Logic, 32 North Holland.
      </para>
      <para>
        Cartmell J. (1986) 
        Formalising the Network and Hierarchical Data Models - an Application of Categorical Logic, 
        in Category Theory and Computer Programming, Lecture Notes in Computer Science 240, Springer-Verlag.
      </para>
      <para>
        Alderson A. and Cartmell J. (1987) 
        The Eclipse Two-Tier Database Interface, 
        in ESEC’87 Proceedings of the 1st European Software Engineering Conference, Strasbourg, Springer-Verlag, 1987.
      </para>
      <para>
        Cartmell J. (1988) 
        The Evaluation of Project Support Environments for the STARTS USER GUIDE,
        in Software Engineering Environments, Ellis Horwood.
      </para>
      <para>
        Cartmell J. and Alderson A. (1988) 
        The Eclipse Data Model - A Functional Account,
        in Software Engineering Environments, P.Brereton (Ed.), Ellis Horwood.
      </para>
      <para>
        Alderson A. and Cartmell J. (1989) 
        The Evolution of the Eclipse Kernel, 
        in ECLIPSE An Integrated Project Support Environment, M.F.Bott (Ed.), Peter Peregrinus.
      </para>
      <para>
        Cartmell J. and Alderson A. (1989) 
        The Eclipse Two-Tier Database, 
        in ECLIPSE An Integrated Project Support Environment, M.F.Bott (Ed.), Peter Peregrinus.
      </para>
      <para>
        Alderson A., Elliott A. and Cartmell J. (1990) 
        The Eclipse Programme,
        in Proceedings of the First International Conference on Systems Development Environments and Factories, Berlin 1989, N.Madhavji, W.Schafer and H.Weber (Eds), Springer-Verlag.
      </para>
      <para>
        Alderson A., Cartmell J., Elliott A., (1997), 
        The Concepts Underlying a Meta-CASE Tool,
        SOCTR/97/02, School of Computing, Staffordshire University.
      </para>
      <para>
        Alderson A., Cartmell J., Elliott A., (1997), 
        Data Transformation Based on Data Model Derivation,
        SOCTR/97/03, School of Computing, Staffordshire University.
      </para>
      <para>
        Alderson A., Cartmell J.W. and Elliott A., (1997), 
        On the Scope of Relationships,
        in Proceedings of the Eighth International Workshop on Software Technology and Engineering Practice (STEP  97), London, England 14-18th July 1997, IEEE Computer Society Press, 279-287.
      </para>
      <para>
        Alderson A., Cartmell J.W. and Elliott A., (1999), 
        ToolBuilder: From CASE Tool Components to Method Engineering, 
        Proceedings of COSET’99 (Workshop WTM3 of ICSE’99), 17-18 May 1999, Los Angeles, CA, University of South Austrailia Press, ISBN 0868036293.
      </para>
      <para>
        Cartmell J., Enoch S., Krstajic D., Leahy D.E., (2005), 
        Automated QSAR through Competitive Workflow,
        Journal of Computer-Aided Molecular Design, 19(11):821-33.
      </para>
    </subsection>
  </preface>
</chapter>



