<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<entity_model xmlns="http://www.entitymodelling.org/ERmodel"
               xmlns:era="http://www.entitymodelling.org/ERmodel">

   <include_model filename="ERA..commonDescriptive_text.xml"/>

   <entity_type>
      <name>composition</name>
      <composition> 
         <type>pullback_constraint</type>
         <description>
         <p>
            Specifies a pullback constraint on a composition relationship. This is a certain type of existence assertion.
         </p>
         </description>
      </composition> 
   </entity_type>

   <entity_type>
      <name>pullback_constraint</name>
      <description>
         <p>
            Used to specify a pullback diagram of relationships in which the subject composition relationship participates.
         </p> 
         <p>
            For a discussion of the role of pullback diagrams in entity modelling see section 
            <a href="http://www.entitymodelling.org/tutorialone/pullbacks.html">ExistenceAssertions/Pullbacks</a>
            of the online entity modelling book.
         </p>
      </description>
      <reference>
         <name>projection_rel</name>
         <type>reference?</type>
         <description>
            <p>
               This specifies one of the sides of a pullback diagram.
            </p>
            <p>
               The primary scope for this relationship is shown in the following diagram:
            </p>
            <p>
                  <object id="svg-object"
                           data="pullback_constraint.projection_rel..primary_scope.svg"
                           type="image/svg+xml">filler to stop contraction of this xml element</object>
            </p>
            <p>
               This relationship also has an auxiliary scope which can be illustrated as follows
            </p>
            <p> 
                  <object id="svg-object"
                           data="pullback_constraint.projection_rel..auxiliary_scope.svg"
                           type="image/svg+xml">filler to stop contraction of this xml element</object>
            </p>
         </description>
      </reference>
      <composition>
          <name>along</name>
          <type>navigation</type>
         <description>
            <p>
               This specifies one of the sides of a pullback diagram.
            </p>
            <p>
               This side of the pullback diagram may be a single step along a single-valued relationship
               or a join of such steps. It is specified as an instance of a <i>directional path</i>.
            </p>
            <p> Aside: The name of this relationship comes about because in category theory we may speak of pulling one morphism back along another. In this case it is the dependency chain from the
            <i>corner type</i> which is pulled back along the <i>along</i> path.
         </p>
         </description>
      </composition>
      <reference>
         <name>corner_type</name>
         <type>entity_type</type>
         <description><p>Specifies the entity type which is one of the corners of a pullback diagram.</p></description>
      </reference>
   </entity_type>
</entity_model>