
<chapter>
  <title>ER Script Software</title>
  <subtitle>ER Script <emdash/> Concept to Code</subtitle>
  <label>concept2code</label>
  <explanation> First release of this open source software.
  </explanation>

  <preface>Open source software for scripting ER models and generating code.


    <subsection>
      <title>About this software</title>
      <label>softwareoverview</label>

      <para> This chapter describes entity modelling software designed and written by the author and supporting
    both software and database design and code generation to a modern technology stack. This software 
    is copyright Cyprotex Discovery Ltd. but is made freely available under a GPL v3 license. Before you download it you
    need be aware that <emph>currently</emph> this software does <emph>not</emph> include a graphical user interface, instead ER models
    inclusive of diagrams are scripted <emdash/> they require representation in XML. From the XML, diagrams 
    can be generated in svg format and also in postscript or pdf format using the pstricks latex packages. A variety
    of code generators support implementation in XML, typescript, python and in Google's protocol buffer format.     
      </para>
      <para>
     Code generators inclusive of the diagram generators are written in xslt 2.0 and have been developed and tested using
     the Saxon xslt processor. All the diagrams in this book have been generated this way;  indeed the whole book is generated
     from structured content represented in XML <emdash/> the structure of which content <emdash/> you should have guessed it <emdash/> is 
     described by an ER model. Along the same lines, the XML representation of an ER model has a structure which is described by
     an ER meta model. 
      </para>
      <para> 
     This software is a work in progress. The source code is made freely available on GitHub at <a href="https://github.com/JohnWCartmell/ERmodelSeries1">JohnWCartmell/ERmodelSeries1</a>. Raise an issue on Github
     or contact the author john.w.cartmell on gmail if you would like to get involved.   There is lots to be done but the project is clear and
     the current implementation has been stress-tested, so to speak, in the development of business critical laboratory workflow systems at
     Cyprotex Discovery Ltd. To the software developer I say that to utilise this software you need to be bought into, or to be open to an idea of 
     a smooth path from <emph>concept to code</emph>, to the ideas of Computer Aided Software Engineering (CASE) and, as a corollary, to the idea of 
     meta-CASE. The software implements the novel ideas described in the relational design section of this book <emdash/>
    as a user you can model scope and eliminate data normalisation <emdash/> you get a smoother road, concept to code.  
      </para>     
    <para>The following development work is in progress:
      <itemize>
        <item>Improved scripting of diagrams <emdash/> this is the highest priority.</item>
        <item>Support for universals and reference by type.</item>
        <item>Support for recursive identification.</item>
        <item>Support for rules.</item>
        <item>Though the relational concepts are all there, the final translation into SQL has not been programmed as yet.</item>  
      </itemize>      
      </para>
    </subsection>

    <subsection>
      <title>ERScript Release 3</title>
      <label>erscriptr3</label>

      <para> 
    First public release of this software.  Click 
    <a  href="ERScript_r3.zip" target="_blank"
                        onclick="ga('send', 'event', 'Software', 'Download', this.href);">
                              here</a>
    to download. 
    This is a zip file containing the ER modelling software and also containing Saxon and Jing jar files <emdash/> each of these have their own specific license conditions and
    these are included in the download. 
      </para>
    </subsection>
  </preface>




</chapter>

